Guide to the Lowell Turrentine Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Lowell Turrentine papers
1913-1956
SC0057
Turrentine, Lowell.
4 Linear feet
Collection pertains largely to his professional life at Stanford University and contains correspondence, both business and personal; his master's thesis; materials for lectures; degrees, awards, and certificates; and a Turrentine genealogy. General correspondence concerns financial investments, legal issues (including estate issues), law curriculum, publication of his articles and books, placement of law students, and personal affairs such as his health, offers of other teaching posts, and Princeton and Harvard reunions. There is a substantial amount of correspondence and memoranda from his work as a Compliance Commissioner for the War Production Board, 1942-44. Other topics include the Stanford Law Veterans Memorial Scholarship, the death of Allene Lamson, Laisne v. State Board of Optometry, and the effect of World War II on the Law School. Correspondents include Warren Christopher, Felix Frankfurter, Charles A. Beardsley, John S. Bradway, Elliott E. Cheatham, Juan Enrique Geigel, Erwin N. Griswold, Moffatt Hancock, Marion R. Kirkwood, Ray B. Lyon, Philbrick McCoy, D. O. McGovney, Roscoe Pound, Owen J. Roberts, Malcolm P. Sharp, Fred Ames Weller, and Richard Wicks.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift of Lowell Turrentine, 1969.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Lowell Turrentine earned his undergraduate degree at Princeton in 1917 and his law degrees at Harvard in 1922 and 1929. He practiced law in Cleveland and New York City and was involved in the prosecution of the Elk Hills and Teapot Dome scandal, before joining the faculty of the Stanford Law School in the fall of 1929. During World War II he served as compliance commissioner for the War Production Board. He was acting dean of the law school in 1945-46; in 1958 he became the first holder of the Marion Rice Kirkwood Professorship in Law. He retired in 1961 and died in 1992.
Description of the Collection
Collection pertains largely to his professional life at Stanford University and contains correspondence, both business and personal; his master's thesis; materials for lectures; degrees, awards, and certificates; and a Turrentine genealogy. General correspondence concerns financial investments, legal issues (including estate issues), law curriculum, publication of his articles and books, placement of law students, and personal affairs such as his health, offers of other teaching posts, and Princeton and Harvard reunions. There is a substantial amount of correspondence and memoranda from his work as a Compliance Commissioner for the War Production Board, 1942-44. Other topics include the Stanford Law Veterans Memorial Scholarship, the death of Allene Lamson, Laisne v. State Board of Optometry, and the effect of World War II on the Law School. Correspondents include Warren Christopher, Felix Frankfurter, Charles A. Beardsley, John S. Bradway, Elliott E. Cheatham, Juan Enrique Geigel, Erwin N. Griswold, Moffatt Hancock, Marion R. Kirkwood, Ray B. Lyon, Philbrick McCoy, D. O. McGovney, Roscoe Pound, Owen J. Roberts, Malcolm P. Sharp, Fred Ames Weller, and Richard Wicks.
Access Terms
Beardsley, Charles Alexander, 1882-1963.; Bradway, John S. (John Saeger), 1890-1985; Cheatham, Elliott Evans, 1888-1972.; Christopher, Warren.; Frankfurter, Felix, 1882-1965.; Geigel, Juan Enrique.; Griswold, Erwin N. (Erwin Nathaniel), 1904-; Hancock, Moffatt.; Kirkwood, Marion Rice, 1887-1978.; Kreps, Theodore J. (Theodore John ), b. 1897; Lamson, Allene.; McCoy, Philbrick, 1897-; McGovney, Dudley O. (Dudley Odell), 1877-1947.; Pound, Roscoe, 1870-1964.; Roberts, Owen J. (Owen Josephus), 1875-1955.; Sharp, Malcolm Pitman, 1897-; Stanford University. School of Law--Faculty.; Turrentine, Julian.; Turrentine, Lawrence N.; Turrentine, Lowell.; United States. War Production Board.; Weller, Fred Ames.; Wicks, Richard.; Law --Study and teaching.; Universities and colleges--Faculty.; World War, 1939-1945--California--Stanford.; World War, 1939-1945--Economic aspects--United States.
Collection Contents
- Papers
  - Correspondence, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1942 Jan. – Mar. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1942 Apr. – June (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1942 July – Sept. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1942 Oct. – Dec. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1943 Jan. – Mar. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1943 Apr. – June (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1943 July – Sept. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1943 Oct. – Dec. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1944 Jan. – Mar. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1944 Apr. – June (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1944 July – Oct. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1944 Nov. – Dec. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1945 Jan. – June (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1945 July – Dec. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1946 Jan. – May (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1946 June – Dec. (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1948 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1949 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1950 Jan. – Mar. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1950 April – June (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1950 July – Dec. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1951 Jan. – June (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1951 July – Dec. (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1952 Jan. – May (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1952 June – Dec. (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1953 Jan. – March (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1953 Apr. – June (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1953 July – Dec. (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1954 Jan. – June (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1954 July – Dec. (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1955 Jan. – June (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1955 July – Dec. (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1956 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence with Benjamin F. Crump re Standard Equities Corp. stock, 1936-43 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence with Philbrick McCoy re law handbook co-authorship, 1935-36; includes outline of book and contract (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence re law scholarship committee, 1948-50 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Law Library minutes, 1932 May and October (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence with Raymond F. Lillie, 1938-42, with a few letters from Gilberta Lillie (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence re Practicing Law Institute, 1941-46 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence re class on social legislation, 1941-46; correspondents include Walter P. Armstrong and Ray B. Lyon (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Directed research papers by students, 1933-1949 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Genealogy of Turrentine family and clippings (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Historical jurisprudence – mimeographed typescript, pp. 1-69 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Historical jurisprudence – mimeographed typescript, pp. 70-158 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Historical jurisprudence – mimeographed typescript, pp. 159-213 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Bessie Manuel papers (estate matter), 1944-46 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Master's thesis, "'Separable Controversy' as a Ground for Removal to the Federal Courts of Certain Types of Cases Involving Interests in Land," 1929 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Material re state constitution amendment #9, 1940 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Personal correspondence and papers, 1913-1918 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Personal correspondence and papers, 1924-1929 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Personal correspondence, Felix Frankfurter, 1938-41 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Personal correspondence and papers, 1930-1938 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Personal correspondence and papers, 1941-1949 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Personal correspondence and papers, undated (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Pound, Roscoe: Readings in Roman Law, Second Edition Part I, 1914; Outlines of Lectures on Jurisprudence, Fourth Edition, 1928 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Degrees, awards, certificates, 1922-1950Degrees, awards, certificates, 1922-1950 (Box 8)
General correspondence index (not inclusive)
Beardsley, Charles A. 1 4-6 1931-33
Bradway, John S. 1 6-8 1933-35
Bradway, John S. 5 3 1953 Dec.
Carmen, W. B., Jr. 2 4 1942 Apr.
Christopher, Warren [to George Grimes] 4 2 1949
Cranston, John M. 4 4-5 1950 May, Nov.
Cranston, John M. 4 8 1952 Feb.
Crothers, George E. 1952-53 (4/8 – 5/3)
Curran, J. E. [re son James B. Curran] 3 5 1945 Feb.,
Curran, J. E. [re son James B. Curran] 4 1 1948 Feb.
Curran, James B. (former student in Armed Services) 2 5-6 1942 Sept., Dec.
Chandler, George G. 1 2 1929
Cheatham, Elliott E. 4 3 1950 Jan.
Cheatham, Elliott E. 5 6-7 1955
Doty, William S. 1 12 1939
Ervin, John W. 4 3 1950 Jan.
Fletcher, Robert L. 5 6-8 1955-56
Frankfurter, Felix 2 3 1942 Jan.
Frankfurter, Felix 2 7 1943 Jan.
Geigel, Juan Enrique 8-9 1935-1936,
Geigel, Juan Enrique 2 5 1942 (Sept.)
Genser, Joseph (former student in Armed Services) 2 6 1942 Dec.,
Genser, Joseph (former student in Armed Services) 2 8 1943 Apr.
Griswold, Erwin N. 1 41038 1932-36
Griswold, Erwin N. 1 12 1939
Griswold, Erwin N. 2 7 1943 (Feb.)
Griswold, Erwin N. 4 8 1952 Feb.
Griswold, Erwin N. 5 1 1953 Mar.
Griswold, Erwin N. 5 5 1954 Dec.
Hahn, Herbert L. 5 1-7 1953-55
Hancock, Moffatt 5 1 1953 Mar.
Kirkwood, Marion R. 1 4 1931
Kreps, Theodore J. 2 1 1940
Lyon, Ray B. 3 1-2 1942 Jan., June
Lyon, Ray B. 4 8 1952 Apr.
Lyon, Ray B. 5 4 1954 Feb
Lyon, Ray B. 5 41067 1955 June, Dec.
Lyon, Ray B. 5 8 1956 June
McCoy, Philbrick (with tss "The Law Student and Professional Standards") 5 1 1953 Jan.
McCoy, Philbrick 6 2
McGovney, D. O. 2 2 1941
McGovney, D. O. 2 3-4, 6 1942 (Mar., May, June, Oct.)
Pound, Roscoe 4 2 1949
Roberts, Owen J. 1 4-5, 9, 12
Roberts, Owen J. 1942 Feb.
Root, Clark, Buckner & Ballantine (law firm) 1 4-9 1931-36
Alyea, Ethan 1 8-9 1935-36
Alyea, Ethan 4 4-5 1950 (May, Nov)
Alyea, Ethan 4 8 1952 (Feb., May)
Alyea, Ethan 5 1-8 1953-Jan. 56
Laporte, Lloyd 1 12 1939
Root, Elihu, Jr. 2 1 1940
Sharp, Malcolm P. 2 6 1942 Oct.
Sharp, Malcolm P. 5 7-8 1955 Dec.; 1956 Jan.
Turrentine, Julian 1 2-3 1929-30
Turrentine, Lawrence N. 1 9 1936
War Production Board 2 & 3 1942-1945
Weller, Fred Ames [also of Root firm] 1 4-9 1931-36
Wicks, Richard 5 4-7 1954-55
Outgoing Letters of Note
Christian Science, refuting its approach to medicine 1 4 1931
Father's 70th birthday (Rev. Francis M. Turrentine) 1 4 1931
Death of Allene Lamson [evidence refutes accident] 1 7 1934
World War II, effect on Law School 2 3-6 1942
Evacuation of Japanese & Japanese Americans 2 3-6 1942
SU's Civilian Defense Plan 2 4 1942 May
To Mrs. Morie Takasuka and her son Kazuo Takasuka (while in relocation camps) 2 6-7 1942 Oct. – 1943 Mar.
Report on his work as Compliance Commissioner 3 5 1945 May
Other topics of note:
Report on his work as Compliance Commissioner 1945 May
Laisne v. State Board of Optometry 1942
Stanford Law Veterans Memorial Scholarship 1945
AAUP matters (national and at SU) 1953 May